<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A short answer to several questions proposed to a gentleman of quality by a great minister of state not unfit for these times of our continuing divisions, though written when a general indulgence of all opinions was endeavoured to be obtained : shewing the authors judgement concerning the publick exercise of several religions and forms of worship, either upon pious or prudential grounds, under one and the same government : as they may relate both to discipline and doctrine, ceremonials or essentials in worship.</title>
            <author>Monson, John, Sir, 1600-1683.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1678</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 56 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A51171</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M2463</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R8157</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13520004</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13520004</idno>
            <idno type="VID">99905</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A51171)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 99905)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 467:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A short answer to several questions proposed to a gentleman of quality by a great minister of state not unfit for these times of our continuing divisions, though written when a general indulgence of all opinions was endeavoured to be obtained : shewing the authors judgement concerning the publick exercise of several religions and forms of worship, either upon pious or prudential grounds, under one and the same government : as they may relate both to discipline and doctrine, ceremonials or essentials in worship.</title>
                  <author>Monson, John, Sir, 1600-1683.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 22 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1678.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to Monson by Wing and Halkett and Laing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church and state --  England.</term>
               <term>Concord --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Religious tolerance --  History --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:99905:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Short ANSWER To ſeveral QUESTIONS PROPOSED To a Gentleman of Quality, by a Great Miniſter of State; not unfit for theſe times of our continuing Diviſions (though Written when a General Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence of all Opinions was endeavoured to be obtained). Shewing the Authors judgement concerning the publick exerciſe of ſeveral Religions and forms of Worſhip (either upon Pious or Prudential grounds) under one and the ſame Government; as they may relate both to Diſcipline and Doctrine, Ceremonials or Eſſentials in Worſhip.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed, In the Year, 1678.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:99905:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:99905:2"/>
            <p>AS Kings reign by God, ſo they ſhould rule for him and the higheſt good of their people, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally in matters of Religion, both in maintaining the ſubſtance and all eſſential parts of it, in their vigour and power, by compulſion (in ſome caſes) and humane reſtraint to force the outward man to obedience in things that are good in themſelves:</p>
            <p>And for the preſervation of unity, to preſcribe ſuch Rules, Methods and boundaries in things indifferent, as may bring all to uniformity in worſhip, and ſtand as a wall or fence to Gods Vineyards, againſt the invaſions of the little Foxes of Schiſms and Factions.</p>
            <p>And this is to be done, not only for decency, order, and ſignificancy; but for the preſervation of Religion it ſelf. For though they are not parts of it, but Circumſtantials; Eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tials in a well formed Church cannot be maintained without them, no more than a Tree can be preſerved to live without its Bark, or Majeſty in a King without Reverence; for that (as the skin to the body) preſerves it both in being and beauty: which occaſioned St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s precept, of having all things done decently and in order, that is, according to appointment, as the original will bear it (for ſo Dr. <hi>Hamond</hi> renders the word)
<note n="a" place="margin">1 Cor. 14.40.</note> And take but away thoſe Regulations of our publick de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votions (which are as the hem that ſtrengthens the Garment, and keeps it uniform) all would reſolve into Rents and Schiſms, Chaos and Confuſion.</p>
            <p>For if the Church of God (his encloſed Garden) be not fenced by good Laws for Conformity, all methods of Devotion are loſt, and the Boars of the Forreſt (unruly men of factious ſpirits) will ſoon break in to deſtroy and root it up, and offer nothing but the blind and lame to God, in looſe and untruſt poſtures; unbecoming the greatneſs of earthly Princes in our addreſſes to them, (and much more to our God)
<note n="b" place="margin">Mal. 1.</note> by it to make their ſuperiors bend to them, if pertinacious obſtinacy can do it, when they ſhould bow to their ſuperiors;
<note n="c" place="margin">Rom. 13. 1 Pet. 2. Eph. 4. and 6.</note> according to the Oeconomy of nature it ſelf, where the inferiour Orbs are
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:99905:3"/>to be guided by the higheſt Spheres; otherwiſe the whole fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brick would be unhinged and fall in pieces, or at leaſt grow weak by ſeperation: So as a diſpenſation to ſeveral forms of worſhip in one Church, muſt prove an Act rather of Diviſion than Comprehenſion, and encreaſe emulations and factions (not advance Piety, but plant a Seminary for a continued Schiſm): Nay, there could be no ſuch encouragement given, but there would be ſcandal and a way of Seduction in it, (in that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velties never want Courtſhip and Adorers) and therefore the old way is <hi>Regia via,</hi> Gods way, and only to be contended for;
<note n="a" place="margin">St. <hi>Jude</hi> Ep.</note> as it is endeavoured by our Act of Uniformity.</p>
            <p>And in this reſpect, Kings and Queens are chiefly ſtiled Nur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Fathers and Nurſing Mothers to the Church; Fathers for proviſion and protection; Mothers, for their tenderneſs and care, who by little ſtratagems and circumventions, many times bring their Children to an habituated obedience, and keep dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers from them by ſome outward and extraordinary confine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, both for honeſty and order
<note n="b" place="margin">1 Cor. 14.40.</note>.</p>
            <p>And for that end, Kings have no meaner a <hi>Depoſitum</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to them, than the Crown and Scepter of God and Chriſt in the Church: for they are as the Lyons about the Throne to ſecure and guard it; and as Lawgivers in indifferent things
<note n="c" place="margin">Deut. 33.4,5.</note> (though ſubject to the direction (not compulſion) both of Gods Laws and their own) ought with
<hi>David</hi> to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe rules for fixed Services and Devotion
<note n="d" place="margin">1 Chron. 23.</note>, and with
<hi>Joſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah,</hi> to compel to Religious duties, and the Laws of their own Kingdoms (as <hi>Hezekiah</hi> did)
<note n="e" place="margin">2 Chron. 34.33.</note>, which
<hi>Conſtantine</hi> the firſt Chriſtian Emperor imitated
<note n="f" place="margin">Euſeb. <hi>de vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta</hi> Conſtant.
<hi>Lib.</hi> 2. chap. 37, 38, 39.</note>; but good Kings never impoſed on any the viſions of their own fancies, nor Licenſed the crude and unnouriſhing vapours of others empty wits (it being below the Majeſty of Truth and Religion to do it), but acted according to the Rule of Gods Law; not ſuffering mens luſt to guide them, which ever brings unconſtancy with it, and maketh the ſoul like a diſtempered body, never well in any poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or condition: for then Men (like Bees from one flower to another) will be ever flying from one change to another, and not find enough to ſatiate the intemperate deſires of change (as is obſerved by a learned Man).</p>
            <p>So as it can neither be agreeable to Religion nor Prudence, for a King to ſuffer variety of Doctrines (or forms in the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:99905:3"/>exerciſe of Religion, though in middle things Supreme power chiefly conſiſts). But more particularly,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> Kings ought to maintain purity in the doctrinal, pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctical and eſſential parts of Religion (without any publick in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgence or diſpenſations) as that only which can maintain them
<note n="a" place="margin">Prov. 16.12,20,28.</note> and their Kingdoms,
<note place="margin">Ez. 33. Eccleſ. 10.</note> and (as
<hi>Elijah</hi>) will prove Chariots and Horſemen for their ſecurity; there being no guard to that of piety and zeal for Gods Glory, which they are intruſted to preſerve, (even both Tables of the Law) and are not in that caſe to bear the Sword in vain, which is put into their hands for that uſe;
<note n="b" place="margin">Ezra 7. 2 Chron. 34.33.</note> compulſion being in ſome caſes neceſſary (as protection in others) where commands are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temned
<note n="c" place="margin">Luke 14.23. Rev. 2.2,6. 6.14,15,20. Ch.
3.15,16.</note>.</p>
            <p>Nor doth Chriſts permiſſion of the Tares to grow, give any juſt power of toleration (to Princes by Gods Law) in known evils; or forbid puniſhing of pertinacious contumacy againſt lawful commands; but only permits and exempts mixed Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies (and ſuch men as have dangerous opinions, and conceal them) where by reaſon of outward Conformity, none can diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criminate the truly Pious and Orthodox, from the Hypocrite; nor doth he forbid their eradication abſolutely, but for fear the good ſeed ſhould alſo be deſtroyed; when a connivence to known errors in Doctrine (or to pertinacious Non-Conformiſts in indifferent things) would make the Magiſtrates contract the guilt of their crimes, <hi>Judg.</hi> 5.23; by confirming one in their miſtaken Doctrines by ſuch indulgence, and the other in their ſuperſtitious believing indifferent things unlawful; to an adore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Idol of their own fancy, and uncharitably cenſuring of all others (even the Church and Government it ſelf) though they bring Hell out of Heaven by it, under pretence of devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and the Devil to Rule amongſt us in <hi>Samuels</hi> Garment, by the ſilly charms of a ſeducing ſpirit, through the warmth of zeal, when it wants the light of knowledg to guide it. For Zeal, if irregular, like the volatile ſpirits of poyſons when unconfined (by not being luted up in ſome Viol or Veſſel) evaporates into an airy being, only to infect others that ſuck it in by nearneſs of converſation: ſo as ſome ingredients of a ſeeming cruelty in our Laws, may prove the moſt merciful and ſoveraign remedy (both to reduce and recover them, and preſerve the found from their contagion) if tempered in a proportion to their crimes, by<pb n="4" facs="tcp:99905:4"/>
               <hi>pecunary</hi> mulcts, or other confinements; <hi>ſaving ſome by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion, others by fear</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Jude 22.23. Eſra 7.</note>, when the violation of any juſt Law, if wilfully done, is owned unlawful; and that the leaſt minute attom, or airy omiſſion, if habitual, may become the greateſt crime, if done with ſcandal and contempt to Authority; in that the trranſgreſſion is againſt Gods Ordinance, that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth obedience to the Commander, and conſiſts not in the value of the thing commanded by him (it being no leſs Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to coyn a Farthing that hath the Kings ſtamp upon it, than a piece of Gold) according to our Saviours Rule; In that, he that wilfully offends in one, is guilty of the breach of all the Commandments; and upon equal temptation would break the reſt: For one little wilful ſin (like the firſt drop in an orifice) will uſher in more, and diſpoſe the whole body to ſuch evacua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and eruptions.</p>
            <p>2. In prudence (I affirm in general, That) there ought to be no Indulgence as to the publick exerciſe of any falſe Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, or to variety of forms in outward worſhip: For what ſafety, unity, decency, or order can there be, in ſetting up one Congregation againſt another; when order is the bond of peace that keeps all in unity? For once break that, or tye it but with a ſlip-knot, and all will be diſſolved and come to confuſion; which is the womb of Rebellion and Schiſms; (ſo Biſhop <hi>Laud</hi> expreſſes it.)</p>
            <p>Nay, ſuch a liberty were to depoſe Reaſon (the ſupreme Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch) and enthrone the inferior members, which ſhould ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit, and not impoſe; and certainly the doing any thing forced (in ſuch a duel and contention) would give courage and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolency to the enemy to preſs for more: for if the paile of the Law hath ſuch a breach once made in it, it will let in all the Beaſts of the Foreſt to Rapine and Prey, to the loſs of good Subjects, or their diſſatisfaction, but not to the making of any other better.</p>
            <p>Yet wiſe Princes may, in regular ways, enlarge any thing that is too ſtrait in matter of Diſcipline; but they never ought to let clamour, or the unjuſt diſcontents of any, to midwife in what they call Reformation; and much leſs a Tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of all Sects and Errors: Nor can a King rationally ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect a harmony amongſt Antipathies, by permitting ſeveral forms in one ſetled Government; though the want of power to<pb n="5" facs="tcp:99905:4"/>maintain his own Laws, may force him poſſibly at ſome times to unreaſonable (not unlawful) condeſcentions (when a dam againſt that current would but inrage it to greater violences).</p>
            <p>Yet in ſuch a caſe, I conceive, he ought rather to make a general Rule of Conformity for all in indifferent things, if poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible (than differing ones to parties), by it to lay aſleep and bury all animoſities the other would maintain, and like oyl upon Paper, would rather harden than ſoften ſuch rebellious ſpirits; and render them rather Conquerors than Suppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cants.</p>
            <p>But I hope God will not ſubmit his own Glory, and our King, to ſuch an Eclipſe (though probably it may be attempted; and ill Schemes, by ſome propoſed and calculated for our <hi>Hori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zon,</hi> ſince His Majeſties compliance in ſome things hath made them rather impoſe more, than acquieſce in what they deſired); for he that once gives ground, ever loſes more in his retreat; (unleſs it be to rally again with ſome reſerves to maintain his own right more vigorouſly); ſo as we ought ſtill to contend to blood, for our Kings freedom in his actings againſt ſuch, eſpecially thoſe whoſe Principles are for Reſiſtance and Rebellion (not ſubmiſſion) in things that are contrary to their ſeditious and ſuperſtitious judgements: and hold it lawful to murder the King (if not the man) in whom the Regal power is veſted, by diſpoiling him of all his <hi>Regalia,</hi> and eſſentials of Royalty. For to allow ſuch liberty, were to unſhakkle mad-men, and ſet them free to fury and rage, for the deſtruction of thoſe that would but endeavour their recovery and preſervation; and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flame or ſtrike ſparks into thoſe brands that need be quenched, leſt they heighten all into a flame.</p>
            <p>Nay all forced and irregular condeſcentions would reflect diſhonour and diſgrace upon our Government and Governours, and diſcouragement to all Orthodox Profeſſors, if his Majeſty ſhould not maintain (againſt clamour and violence) what hath been ſetled and proſperouſly practiſed amongſt us ſince the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, and hath had the influences of Heaven formerly, to give it a prolifick vertue, in producing a loyal, zealous, and pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous people to beautifie their profeſſions: And Chriſtian Kings ſhould not be out-done by Heathens (inſpired by God to it) but ſend out their Decrees, That whoſoever will not do the Law of God, and the Kings Laws (which are not contrary to
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:99905:5"/>it) ſhould have judgement without delay, whether it be to Death, or to Baniſhment, or to confiſcation of Goods, or to Impriſonment,
<note n="a" place="margin">Ezra 7.25,26,27.</note> (according to the nature of the offence) which was in part practiſed by the Kings of
<hi>Iſrael,</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">2 Chron. 15.12,13,14,15, and 29, &amp; 30, &amp; 31, &amp; 34.31,32,33. 1 Chron. 23.</note> and ought the more to be done (in ſome Caſes) under the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, that hath more of light and direction in it to walk by; leſt liberty ſhould turn into licentiouſneſs, in holding things con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the analogy of Faith, and againſt the Rules of Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, Purity, Loyalty, Sobriety and Expedience, to the diſturb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of the Peace and Unity of the Church and State; which good and pious Kings ought always to prevent or reſtrain, by wholeſom and penal Laws of Regulation, to fright their people the more to their duties and obedience: for ſome are to be ſaved as by fire, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.15.</p>
            <p>So as toleration of all Opinions and Sects, (were a cruel mercy, and) would leave men to ſet up the Trophies of their own ruines, and to adore the idols of their own fancies; nay, it would increaſe factions, diſſolve unity, and ſet every one free to make Luſt his Law, and diſarm the Magiſtrate (or make him bear the Sword in vain); it would legitimate and infran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſe all Errors, Schiſms, Idolatry, Hereſies, and Atheiſtical Principles, and let in Judgements upon a Nation, and contract a crime, not only by the indulging it; but the Governour would appropriate to himſelf the guilt of all others ſins that are acted under ſuch a licentious freedom: For though good Laws do not always reform Errors in others, yet they make their crimes not epidemical nor imputable to the Governor of a Nation if executed; whereas connivence or toleration intitles the ſupream Magiſtrates to the others ſins and puniſhments; as it would do the guilt of innocent blood in Murtherers, if it were not forbidden by human Laws and puniſhed, though they many times prevent them not; for where there is no reſtraint, ſin rides in ſtate, as in its Empire, (as in <hi>Iſrael</hi>) when there was no King to hinder men from acting according to the Luſt of their own hearts; which freedom is the greateſt and worſt ſervitude; for we may be left ſometime to the Devil for good, but never to our ſelves, but for deſtruction: However, if a general Toleration to all Religions ſhould at any time be granted upon human and prudential (it can never be juſtified upon pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and Divine) Principles; but would have a combination<pb n="7" facs="tcp:99905:5"/>and complication of many ſins in it, and ever prove the proſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted and pregnant womb of all diſorder and licentiouſneſs.</p>
            <p>Yet I am not in ſome Caſes wholly againſt all Indulgence to perſons of ſober and ſafe Principles, differing only in points of ceremony and outward forms, from the Government eſtabliſhed by Law, though it be to the allowing ſome few places for publick exerciſe of their devotion, they Preaching nothing con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the Thirty nine Articles of our Church, with an exemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of them from all Oaths (and uſe of ceremonies) but thoſe of Allegiance and Supremacy; under ſuch other Rules for regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, as the ſupreme Magiſtrate ſhall think fit; with an exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of them from all preferments of dignity, truſt and profit, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in Church or State, till they conform to the eſtabliſhed Government of our Church; and this only probationally, for ſome fixed time, where the publick peace and ſafety of a Nation depends on it; for then in things indifferent in their nature, and in that part of Government that is prudential only, neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty may make it elegible, and there may be a diſpenſation inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent, and not ſinful, in the Supreme Magiſtrate, though not in them that force it: and ſuch a misfortune ſometimes may im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove the piety and activity of the Orthodox Clergy, perhaps, if they will make advantage of an enemy, by a holy contention for precedency in all vertues that may add luſtre, and gain re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence to their Callings (competition making men the more holy and regular in their comportment, many times, when they would otherways perhaps be more delated and open in their converſation, and more expoſed to exceptions, if a cenſorious eye were not upon them).</p>
            <p>But to allow the leaſt evil of ſin in our ſelves or others, for the producing the greateſt imaginable good, is in no caſe juſtifia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble: Nay, the not oppoſing all things that are ſinful (in our ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral callings and capacities, ſo far as is lawful) contracts their guilt (<hi>Judg.</hi> 5.) for I may betray a fundamental truth by my ſilence; and cannot be innocent, if I wilfully connive at, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to any thing that is contrary to it, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.11, for the higheſt end: (yet the Ark it ſelf muſt fall, rather than be ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported by <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>zzahs</hi> hands) 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 6.6. <hi>Rev.</hi> 22. <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.8. (1
<hi>Sam.</hi> 15, or any unjuſtifiable means; for though many things may be lawful, and not expedient; nothing can be expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient, that is not lawful).</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:99905:6"/>Nay, I may not only appropriate others ſins
<note n="a" place="margin">Pſal. 50.28.</note> by counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, approbation, or imitation (while living) but may be guilty of ſin in others many thouſand years after I am dead, (as well as I did ſin before I was born) when they ſin by my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nivence, example, or infuſion of ill Principles derived from me: for as the long precogitation upon any ſin with delight, makes it an old and inveterate one, before it be produced into act; ſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nothers repetition of any ſin by my example or authority (though committed many ages hence) makes it a new ſin to me, and to encreaſe my damnation (ſo Dr. <hi>Dunn</hi>), as is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced moſt juſtly by Divines from the Parable of <hi>Dives</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Luke 16.</note> who reflected upon himſelf (not his brethren, in his cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity).</p>
            <p>So as with St. <hi>Bernard</hi> to <hi>Eugenius</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ber. de con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſid.</hi> Lib. 3.</note> all our actions re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire, <hi>trinam conſiderationem,</hi> a threefold conſideration, as a moſt learned Divine obſerves to me, <hi>an liceat, an deceat, an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pediat,</hi> to teach us, that diſcretion, charity, and edification, ſhould be ingredients into all our actions: Nay <hi>(Quorum uſus coercetur certis circumſtantiis, ea dicuntur, non expedire; non dicuntur, non licere)</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">
                  <hi>Chamier.</hi> 3. <hi>Panſerat</hi>
21.27.</note> all circumſtances are to be conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in lawful things, as times, places, perſons, meaſure, manner, to the making up of a lawful Action; otherwiſe a right end, without theſe, frees not the action from being ſinful in the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er:
<note n="e" place="margin">
                  <hi>Aug.</hi> 4. <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra. Julian</hi>
3.</note> for though lawfulneſs in a ſtrict ſenſe looks but at the nature and quality of the thing it ſelf, expedience doth weigh all circumſtances that conduce to any end; ſo as both ſhould concur in our actions, which have a voice in them. For with St. <hi>Auguſtine, Quod eſt ſecundum ſe malum ex genere nullo modo poteſt eſſe bonum &amp; licitum:</hi> Becauſe as <hi>Aquinas</hi> ſaith, <hi>Ad hoc quod aliquid ſit bonum requiritur quod omnia recte concurrant;</hi> in that <hi>(bonum eſt ex cauſa integra malum vero ex ſingularibus de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectibus:)</hi> a ſingle defect makes an action ſinful, when all cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances are required to concur in a good one
<note n="f" place="margin">Pſal. 94.20.</note>: In that <hi>omne verum eſt omni vero conſentiens &amp; quicquid non licet certe non oportet</hi> (ſo <hi>Cicero</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">Pro. Balbo.</note>.</p>
            <p>And no preſidents of others acting to the contrary (though ſome do urge it) ought to be an Authority for us to imitate, when the lawfulneſs or unlawfulneſs of no Action is to be ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon matter of fact, though done by the Saints of God them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; in that they are to be conſidered as men (Chriſtiany<pb n="9" facs="tcp:99905:6"/>not deſtroying humanity) ſubject to many weakneſſes and infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities; nay, great failings in particular actions, and may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the more dangerous to others, by the eminency and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation of the perſons that doth them.</p>
            <p>For Religion (as the body) is moſt in hazard when it hath a confluence of ill and noxious humours harboured under a ſeeming healthful complexion; which interrupting the harmony of a well-tempered conſtitution (as one ſaith) at laſt march under the colours of innocency, to the raiſing of a civil mutiny at home, and do draw all the unfound parts into conſpiracy againſt it ſelf; and therefore we ought to be very cautious in our actings, for fear of contracting ſin, there are ſo many Avenues to it.</p>
            <p n="1">As 1. <hi>Conſulendo,</hi> By adviſing others in evil, as <hi>Achitophel</hi> did <hi>Abſolom,</hi> to make good his Treaſon and Rebellion againſt <hi>David;</hi> for ſuch ſhall be taken in their own ſnare, and periſh in or by their own Counſels, ſaith
<hi>Solomon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Adulando,</hi> By feeding others vices, and nurſing them up with the milk of flattery, in calling good evil, and evil good;
<note n="a" place="margin">Iſa. 50.20.</note> which is a beautifying of a people (as the Pagan Negroes do) by painting with Ink inſtead of Colours,
<note n="b" place="margin">Iſa. 9.16.</note> to which the greateſt wo belongs, though the wicked may bleſs for a time thoſe whom God abhorreth
<note n="c" place="margin">Pſal. 10.3.</note>.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Mandando,</hi> So <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>riah's</hi> Murder and Drunkenneſs were <hi>Davids</hi> ſins, though effected by others.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Conſentiendo,</hi> For thus St. <hi>Paul</hi> was guilty of <hi>Stephens</hi> Martyrdom
<note n="d" place="margin">Act: 22.20.</note>; and therefore if ſinners intice thee, conſent thou not
<note n="e" place="margin">Prov. 1.10.</note>: for <hi>ſentient eandem poenam, qui conſentiunt in candem culpam.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5 <hi>Provocando,</hi> By inflaming or inticing others to ſin, as the Harlot in the <hi>Proverbs</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">Prov. 7.</note>; for by ſetting any others houſe on fire, we are ſure to burn and conſume our own, if contiguous to it, and be anſwerable for the others damage.</p>
            <p n="6">6. <hi>Participando,</hi> For if thou ſeeſt a Thief attempting to ſteal, and haſt a power to hinder him, and doſt it not, thou art guilty of his crime; the not preventing ſin in another, where I may do it lawfully, being a promoting of it: And then <hi>[Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quum eſt ut qui participes fuerunt in peccato; participes fiant in ſupplicio]</hi> it is but juſt that we ſuffer in the puniſhment, if we partake in the ſin,
<note n="g" place="margin">Rev. 18.4.</note> for ſo wrath came upon
<hi>Jehoſhaphat</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">2 Chron. 19.2.</note>: for a good wiſh to a bad action, is a partaking of the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil
<note n="i" place="margin">2 Joh. 5.11.</note>.</p>
            <p n="7">
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:99905:7"/>7. <hi>Omittendo vel Conivendo,</hi> by conniving at, or not reproving others in their ſins
<note n="a" place="margin">Eph. 5.11. Lev. 5. Ezek. 3.</note>, ſuch a love and indulgence to my brother, being the greateſt hatred
<note n="b" place="margin">Lev. 19.17.</note>: For ſo God hates us moſt, when he ſeems not to hate us at all, by reproving and correcting us, but ſuffers us to go on in a courſe of wickedneſs
<note n="c" place="margin">Iſa. 1.</note>.</p>
            <p n="8">8. <hi>Defendendo;</hi> for he that defends or maintains a bad cauſe or action, eſpouſeth the guilt of it; when, <hi>He that juſtifyeth the wicked, or condemneth the juſt, is abominable before</hi> (or unto) <hi>God</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Prov. 27.15.</note>, <hi>and becomes the greater ſinner;</hi> in that he hath more of deliberation, and perhaps leſs of temptation in it, than the other had.</p>
            <p n="9">9. <hi>Praecedendo,</hi> by giving ill examples; for if I pluck up the firſt pale in anothers incloſure, and engage others by my ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample to lay it waſte and common, I am guilty of their treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs, as he that wilfully makes or inlarges any cuts in a Sea-bank, is liable to repair the damages any receive by thoſe waters. And thus <hi>Jeroboam</hi> made
<hi>Iſrael</hi> to ſin (ſaith the Text), even <hi>exemplum dando,</hi> as well as <hi>imperando;</hi> and <hi>Peter</hi> the <hi>Jews</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">Gal. 2.</note>.</p>
            <p>And to theſe I might add many other ways (as a learned Divine hath obſerved to me, by which we derive others ſins upon our ſelves) to make us vigilant over our own and others Souls, ſince there are ſo many Avenues for ſin to approach us; and that it is of ſo ſubtil and inſinuating a nature, as (though the Guards be never ſo well kept) it will ſometimes enter by a falſe paſs, or glide in by the advantage of that gloomy darkneſs that ſometimes over-ſhadows the beſt men. And therefore we need add (Ballaſt to our Sail) examination to every action, to poiſe and prove it by; it being a ſafe and noble, no melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cholly thing (as one wittily expreſſes it) to be always in plough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, weeding, and worming a conſcience, in removing (Straws as well as Logs) occaſions of temptations, by trying and teſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing every thought, word, or work, to make them currant, and by filing the Iron, and melting the Ore, to clear and ſmooth the greateſt difficulties, leſt our ſpungy ſouls (apt to receive any liquor) ſuck in and imbrace any thing evil, and ſwell us into ſuch an immence body of ſin, as (through cuſtom or impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitency) may become too big to enter into the <hi>Betheſda</hi> of Chriſts Blood (though what comes there, is ever cleanſed and cured).</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:99905:7"/>But (to expreſs it the better, almoſt in a great Authors words) I conceive a wilful permiſſion or toleration of the moſt atom, airy ſin, is a crime in any man that may prevent it; and much more in a Magiſtrate, who bears the Sword in vain (if he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour not to reſtrain all appearances of evil), and ſheaths it in his own boſom (like
<hi>Ely,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 3.14.) For the Devil brought the Divinity of doing ill, that good might come of it, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.8. early into the Church to undermine and ruin us; and of all other evils, Factions in Religion (if countenanced for any civil end) prove the moſt dangerous; in that, miſtaken zeal hath a Cement in it, that makes the ſtrongeſt Combinations; tyes the cloſeſt, and yet breaks the ſtrongeſt Bonds; violates all Obligations natural and civil; and under a pretence of ſerving God, brings the Devil in upon his ſhoulders, and inthrones him for a Deity, acting all Rapines and Diſorders under a pretence of Piety; ſo as the mutual Communications of Members in ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil bodies, that ſhould be a means of common advantages, is cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted; and men live rather to ſtir up Animoſities, than pay the Duties of Charity to Neighbours, or of Obedience to Superiors; not only to the invaſion of Order and Unity, but the undermi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of Chriſtianity it ſelf, though pretended Religion be the Engine by which they work; and all this to ſhape Government at the laſt for the Intereſt of the ſtrongeſt party; ever pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending to fight for their God, when they fight againſt their King; and glory in their Crime, as the higheſt vertue: ſo as Religion, the great inſtrument of Peace and Piety, proves the greateſt Incendiary.</p>
            <p>For a light diſtemper in the Church, proves many times a Contagion in the State, and is ever to be cured by Corroſives, where Lenitives work not; but with more moderation to thoſe that agree with us (than to ſuch as depart from us) in our ſetled Doctrine, though they artificially pretend to be in theſe times the great Patrons and Vindicators of our Church (by it with the unnatural Viper to eat out the bowels of their own Mother); for there are many now of our High Clergy, that with a ſtrange impudence do intitle her to their Errors (and want not the countenance and encouragements of many great ones to invite them by preferments to it); yet their Arguments are ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Railings, than Reaſons, by ſlighting and defaming our moſt Orthodox Doctrine (concerning Faith, Grace, and Juſtification)<pb n="12" facs="tcp:99905:8"/>with diſowned and falſe conſequences, to make way for the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainment of their dangerous Errors, which are both dero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory to Gods honour, and tend to the ſhaking the ſure founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of our Chriſtian Faith, comfort and aſſurance of our ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Eſtate, by improving <hi>Arminianiſm</hi> (beyond the modeſty of its Author) into great degrees of <hi>Pelagianiſm</hi> and
<hi>Socinia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſm;</hi> and preſs them, as agreeing with the Articles of the Church of <hi>England;</hi> though I dare confidently affirm, that both the Compilers of the Articles, and the eminent men of our Church in ſucceſſion, have ever declared their Judgments of them (con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Election, Juſtification, Renovation, Faith, good Works, Final Perſeverance and Apoſtacy) in all their Writings and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons upon thoſe Subjects, to be otherways (ſome few excepted, and thoſe of late years); and do all agree in a Harmony of Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine with moſt of the reformed Churchs abroad, in thoſe Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nents: As Biſhop <hi>Cranmer, Ridley, Parker, Bale, Jewel, Bilſon, Andrews, Buckeridge, Abbot, Babington, Lake, Sandes, Hall, Morton, Davenet, King, Carleton, Williams, Morly, Perſon, San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſon, Gauden, Reynolds, Ward,</hi> Arch-Biſhop <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher,</hi> and all the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Clergy, and other the moſt eminent men amongſt us; as <hi>Hooker, Feild, Downham, Dun, Jackson, Preſton, Perkins, Featly, Thorndike, Pemble, Meade, Hales,</hi> and infinite others in their Treatiſes upon thoſe Subjects (though ſome of them differ about the Object of Election); ſo as the other
<hi>Noveliſts,</hi> whoſe Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors have now a great poſſeſſion of our Pulpits (by the favour of thoſe that deſign the introducing of their Errors) do now (by ſcandalous Imputations of dangerous Doctrines to others) magiſterially condemn our Orthodox Tenents; and by it (though they preſs outward Conformity and Communion) I believe are the great diſturbers of the Peace of our Church, and cauſes of keeping many of our Anti-Ceremonial Separatiſts from joyning with us; Errors in Doctrine affrighting them more than other circumſtantial things, and makes them look upon us as an Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtatizing Church.</p>
            <p>And therefore I could wiſh ſome care were taken to conform them to the Doctrine of the Articles of our Church (as well as the others to her Diſcipline), at leaſt to ſilence their Pens and Preaching upon thoſe Subjects (according to former Declarati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the late King of bleſſed Memory), as they are more dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, as is conceived, to undermine our Church in her Purity of<pb n="13" facs="tcp:99905:8"/>Doctrine, than the Papiſts themſelves, in that they have the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance of Authority, and inſinuate their opinions by nearer approaches to the Truth, and leſs dangerous conſequences to the civil Power, than the other; though ſome of them have endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured ſeemingly to Preach, though not force us out of our Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prieties, in relation to the Kings Power and Right in them, and might do miſchief, did not the goodneſs both of our Soveraign and Laws, ſecure our intereſt (and provide againſt the ſpreading of ſuch Errors, as well as thoſe of the Papiſts and Sectaries) if duly executed.</p>
            <p>In order to which, for my own judgment, I believe, that if the Laws were fewer and leſs penal, they would prove more ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectual; in that great ſufferings move commiſeration and remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in thoſe that ſhould inſtrumentally execute them, eſpecially where the ſeverity reaches to the undoing of Families, as in Caſes of Recuſancy, for a negative diſobedience in not coming to Church, when milder puniſhments would be more Chriſtian, and perhaps more ſuccesful in order to their compliance.</p>
            <p>But for the reſtrictive part of Laws that ſecure our peace and Church, hinder factious, ſeditious Meetings, Conventicles, or any thing that may countenance or ſpread any erroneous opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons (eſpecially thoſe of the <hi>Papiſts</hi>), I think they cannot be too ſevere, nor too quick in finding out ways to diſcriminate ſuch of them as are boſom and concealed enemies to our Religion and Laws ſtill amongſt us: (yet I wiſh it not ſo much for their pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments, as our own ſecurity) the excluding them (upon ſuch a diſcovery) from all places of Truſt or Power that have any influence upon our Government (but not from the charge of thoſe that are in themſelves poenal): And for that end, I would humbly propoſe ſome Law to be made to the effect follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That all perſons ſuſpected of Recuſancy or Separation from our Church, being preſented for ſuch (at any Quarter-Seſſions where they live) or are thought fit by the Seſſions o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginally without preſentment to be ſummoned thither, ſhall upon notice appear at the next Seſſions after, there held, and there acquit themſelves both by proof upon Oath of having re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the Sacrament in their ſeveral Pariſh-Churches as the Law requires, and take the Oaths of Allegiance and Supremacy then in open Seſſions, or have a Conviction of Recuſancy Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded<pb n="14" facs="tcp:99905:9"/>againſt them as to the ends before mentioned; but not to the forfeiture of their Eſtates, unleſs otherways proceeded againſt upon other poenal Laws that ſhall continue in force; which will both unmask and diſarm them (in a great meaſure) of power to hurt us; and be a ſpeedy and merciful way for their diſcrimination.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That all Benefic'd Parſons and Lecturers, ſhould once in every Three Months be obliged to Read the Articles of our Church in their Desks or Pulpits, before or after Divine Service, in the audience of the Congregation, and there make their ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn proteſtation before God of their conſent and ſubmiſſion to them, and our Homilies, and Common Prayer, as containing the Doctrine and Devotions of the Church of <hi>England;</hi> and that in their moſt literal and genuine ſenſe, which would much remove Jealouſies, ſilence Clamour, and bring them to a Teſt, that deſign and openly wiſh an alteration of them.</p>
            <p>And further, to prevent all the aforementioned and growing miſchiefs, it were well, if ſome further Teſt could be found out to unſcreen and lay open to exception ſuch perſons as by their excellent parts and moralities, gain reputation to their errone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous opinions, and have in effect eclipſed and much leſſened the Grace and Glory of Chriſt, by making Grace and Vertue con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertible, and advancing Natural Religion, at leaſt, to a ſhare in the ſalvation of Man; whereas, though our Church teacheth the ſame neceſſity of a good, moral and pious life (that they alſo aſſert) as fruits and effects of a lively Faith; yet ſhe holds we are ſaved by Faith alone, though not by Faith that is alone, without producing good works; Moral obedience, with in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſanctification, being the only evidences and grounds of a Chriſtians comfort, according to the Articles of our Church: and I think ſuſpenſion (both <hi>ab officio,</hi> and
<hi>beneficio</hi>) is too little for ſuch as own their Mother, and yet wilfully rebel againſt her determinations, and ſcandalouſly defame (by Satyrical in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vectives) thoſe that have been moſt eminent in the Reformation, and in our Church ever ſince; or by bold untruths, would make ſome of the moſt conſiderable amongſt us to patronize errors: Nay, repreſenting St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> himſelf (as more pious than rational) though one of the greateſt Lights, and moſt-to-be Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verenced perſon, both for Prudence, Knowledg, Morality, Piety, Learning, clearneſs of Judgement, and indefatigable Induſtry, that<pb n="15" facs="tcp:99905:9"/>ever lived in the Chriſtian Church, ſince the Apoſtles days; and it hath ever been the boaſt and glory of our Church, to have a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed with his Judgment in our Articles (and therefore with all others, ſo far as they depart not from his Principles, concerning Election, Faith, Juſtification, Sanctification, and good Works); though it is now by ſome made a matter of detraction, ſcorn, and defamation to maintain them Orthodoxly, which certainly ought not to be ſuffered either in our Pulpits or Preſſes by any Licenſed Authority; but rather to give ſome check, or fix ſome mark of diſhonour on them that are ſo inſolently ignorant: or it may in time produce more ſad and open diviſions in our Church, than is generally foreſeen (as it did in
<hi>Scotland</hi> in their firſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion againſt our late Soveraign
<hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt, which was not ſo much occaſioned by the Impoſition of Epiſcopacy and Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies upon them, as by new Doctrine (eſpecially that of <hi>Arminius</hi>) then beginning to receive countenance and encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement both here and there, which I hope the Wiſdom and Piety of our King and Parliament will by Gods mercy prevent; not ſuffering any, either out of profaneneſs, Faction, or the Gay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety of a luxurious Wit, to abuſe and turn the greateſt and moſt ſerious concerns of a Chriſtian into Ridiculous and Burlesk Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity (fitter for a Heathen Stage, than an Orthodox Church to admit of), and are ſo far from a ſober conviction of any real error in others, as they only make Invectives againſt forced and fancied conſequences of their own, drawn from the juſtifyable Tenents of others, who in maintaining Juſtification by Faith a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, include all ſincere, univerſal, and perſevering Obedience, as fruits of it (if true and ſaving), and parts of the Evangelical Covenant, in relation to the qualification of the perſons juſtified; yet in aſcribing the whole work to God of Mans ſalvation, they exclude not Mans co-operation, but make it part of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree, which is irreſpective in regard of the perſon choſen (no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in us moving him), but not in reſpect of the means by which we muſt attain ſalvation; ſo as to us, and for our appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, thoſe Promiſes are wholly conditional, according to the tenure of the Goſpel; but are always the portion of the Elect, by the powerful working of Grace in them, and (as Dr. <hi>Hamond</hi> in his Sermon upon <hi>Matth.</hi> 10.15, phraſeth it) the conſtraining Spirit of God, which by its infinite Charms of mercy, doth controle, convince, and convert the ſinner, and make him con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cur<pb n="16" facs="tcp:99905:10"/>to the making of his calling and election ſure, by a holy perſeverance in the means, (according to that of 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. and 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.) upon all which he enlargeth himſelf in his Sermons upon <hi>Act.</hi> 3.26. <hi>Ez.</hi> 16.30. <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.13.
<hi>Matth.</hi> 1.23. <hi>Jer.</hi> 5.12. <hi>Luk.</hi> 18.2. <hi>Act.</hi>
18.30, but chiefly on <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.15. and 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.15, and keeps harmony with the eminent men and Martyrs of our Church in it, who maintain that Juſtification, as it is Gods Act <hi>in foro divino,</hi> is the eternal emanation of his own goodneſs to his Elect, and conſidereth nothing (objective in them) antecedent to his Decree of their ſalvation, though Faith, Repentance, and Obedience are certain effects and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutive parts of it, in regard of its execution, and is <hi>actio in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diviſibilis,</hi> as it proceeds from Gods Eternal Love, Mercy, and Goodneſs to them in Chriſt. See. Biſ. <hi>Sanderſons</hi> 2 <hi>Ser. ad Cler.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Though conſidering Juſtification (<hi>in foro hominis,</hi> or
<hi>conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entiae</hi>) in reſpect of evidence or actual claim, it is
<hi>(actio divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibilis)</hi> a divided act, and capable of growth and degrees; ſo as the Saints aſſurance of ſalvation, is a property of (though not always inſeparable from) a lively ſaving Faith, and depends upon great manifeſtations and advances in Piety, and may be loſt; but the truly regenerate man cannot fall finally, though he may totally, from Grace, in regard of evidence, and (as Mr. <hi>Hales</hi> of St. <hi>Peters</hi> Fall, Dr.
<hi>Dunn</hi> on <hi>Iſa.</hi> 65.20.) may live in a ſtate of damnation for ſome time, as it ſignifies ſomething againſt the habit of ſanctifying qualities inherent; but never can fall from the Grace of Gods Election, as it ſignifies the grace and favour inherent in the Perſon of God; he may fall from his own Righteouſneſs, but never from Gods purpoſe to ſave him, nor can he loſe the immortal ſeed by which he was begotten, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi>
3. For it is as certain that repentance will follow after any ſin in a man once juſtified, as that good works never go before Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication (according to St. <hi>Aug. de fide &amp; operibus,</hi> our Homily of Juſtification, and the twelfth Article of our Church; yet we are not to judg of our ſelves by Gods Decrees, but our own Actings; yet our Juſtification is not alterable, imperfect, commenſurable only to our Sanctification, and contingent; but as Gods works are intire, done in him at once, and perfected as ſoon as begun; quickned in their conception, and full ſhaped in their quickning; ſo as to Gods Eternity, the laſt Trump is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready ſounded; in that his whole duration is but one permanent<pb n="17" facs="tcp:99905:10"/>point, without parts or diviſion, never changing his will, though he wills and effects a change in his; his purpoſe being his will to ſave them; his predeſtination ordering the means, as Dr. <hi>Dunn</hi> hath it in his Sermon on <hi>Iſa.</hi> 65.20. and <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 2.19.</p>
            <p>Nor doth this Doctrine (as ſome ſcandalouſly aſperſe it) en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage to preſumption, or give hopes of gaining glory, but by the fruits of godlineſs: for God will judg every one according to his works. Yet it is not habitual Juſtice ingrafted, but eternal Juſtice imputed, that juſtifies and infallibly ſaves all the Elect in Chriſt, according to Gods Covenant and revealed Will (ſo learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Hooker</hi> in his diſcourſe of Juſtification) through the impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of his active and paſſive obedience; though our evidence, comfort, and application of it, is founded upon the fruits of San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctification, and Teſtimony of the Holy Spirit with ours (<hi>Rom.</hi> 8.) and not upon Gods Decrees, if conſidered in an abſtracted ſenſe from them: for he ſaves none but by faith, repentance, and obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience; nor damns any, unleſs for a final impenitency againſt means of converſion afforded by God to all within the Pale of the Church; all men being made ſalvable by Chriſts dying for all, and have ſufficient grace given them to work out their ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, if the impediment be not in themſelves (nay efficient alſo in a moral, not phyſical ſenſe), though they want that effectual grace of God by which, and his infinite wiſdom, he doth ſo ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly order and attemper all outward means (in ſuch a congruous manner, and makes ſuch gracious inward applications and inſinu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ations, by the ſecret imperceptible motions and operations of his Holy Spirit into the hearts of his choſen ones), as that, <hi>de facto,</hi> the will ſhall not finally reſiſt; and all this <hi>ex mero beneplacito Dei:</hi> yet there may be <hi>certitudo objecti,</hi> in regard of Gods pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, though not <hi>certitudo ſubjecti,</hi> in regard of the Elects ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſions at all times, as Biſhop <hi>Sanderſon</hi> expreſſes it, which is the ſound, ancient, and Orthodox Tenent of our Church.</p>
            <p>Yet in all this, the will ſuffers no compulſion from God; but he draws, and we run; he inclines, and we imbrace; he ſtrengthens, and we work; or rather not we, but the grace of God in us; for he gives not only a
<hi>(poſſe)</hi> power to will good; as to <hi>Adam</hi> in the ſtate of Innocence; but a <hi>(non poſſe)</hi> power to his Elect, not to will otherways, not to ſin, 1 <hi>John</hi> 3. habitually, or to fall into any preſumptuous ſin, without an actual repentance<pb n="18" facs="tcp:99905:11"/>following, in which Grace ſways ſo powerfully, as if the Will had no freedom in the Action; and the will acts freely, as if grace had no ſway in the Election; yet when we co-operate with grace, only by grace, God not forcing the will, but powerfully and infallibly moving it to determine it ſelf in the performance of all Righteouſneſs, and by Faith to apprehend Chriſts perfect obedience, as imputed to us for the defects in ours, to make us capable of glory, into which no unclean thing muſt enter; nor can any be admitted by the Remiſſion of their ſins only (which freeth but from the pains of Hell) without the Imputation of Chriſts perfect obedience; for he pronounceth not his ſentence at the day of judgment, by (though according unto) his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees; but proceeds judicially to conviction upon evidence, and judgeth and rewardeth all men by, and according to their works; and there being made righteous, by Gods acceptance of Chriſts Righteouſneſs for them, to ſupply the defects of their beſt performances, and perfect the imperfections of their moſt ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere, univerſal, and perſevering obedience. And againſt theſe Truths thus delivered, few amongſt us (that I know of) has the impudence to clamour; but yet there are many learned and rational men that deſign to undermine them, and ſupercili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly and magiſterially do by Inſinuations and artifices ſeem to impoſe new and dangerous notions upon us, by wreſting and ſlighting (not confuting) ours.</p>
            <p n="1">1. By preſſing Moralities, not as fruits and effects of a ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Faith, but as the means (with a general and hiſtorical Faith) to ſave us, when produced by that common and univerſal grace God gives to all mankind in Chriſt; by which Doctrine no man can have a firm aſſurance of his own ſalvation (when <hi>Adam</hi> fell in the ſtate of innocency, without any temptation from within) nor of a viſible Church on Earth, if founded upon no other bottom.</p>
            <p n="2">2. By aſſerting, That Juſtification is conditional, alterable and commenſurate only to our Sanctification (ſo as good works muſt precede it, contrary unto the 11, 12, 13, Articles of our Church; and that a man may fall from it finally (though it be the act of the Judge) when Sanctification is but the qualifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of the perſon juſtified, who may fall from it in ſome de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees,<pb n="19" facs="tcp:99905:11"/>but not totally, Gods Love being free, and as unchange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able as himſelf.</p>
            <p n="3">3. By allowing Chriſts paſſive obedience for the taking away of ſin, but not the imputation of his active obedience for our Juſtification and Salvation; ſo as they differ only from <hi>Socinus</hi> in the firſt part, but come near him in making Chriſts obedience only an Exemplar to us; ours for his ſake to be accepted and rewarded, through the infinite merit of Chriſt (as God and Man) imputed, can only make us capable of an infinite reward, or make our works clean and pure in the ſight of God: For which, read Biſhop <hi>Andrews</hi> Sermon on <hi>Jer.</hi> 23.6, Mr.
<hi>Mead</hi> upon <hi>Matt.</hi> 11.28,29, and on <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2.
<hi>Pſal.</hi> 50, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 38, who agree with St. <hi>Paul</hi> in 1
<hi>Cor.</hi> 1.30, and 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.21, and the great, ancient, and eminent Divines of our Church, ſome of which I have before mentioned.</p>
            <p n="4">4. By maintaining Gods Decree of Salvation to any, is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditional and contingent; ſo as from the contemplation of it, no Child of God, or tender Conſcience, can gather comfort or any aſſurance of ſtability (though they uſe the means to gain it), in that they make the Decree to depend upon the Condition, and the Condition upon the actings and uſe of that general Grace God gives to all, without a more particular and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraining Grace (as D. <hi>Hammond</hi> expreſſeth it) for the deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination of their wills to good; which is contrary to St. <hi>Paul</hi> (<hi>Ep.</hi> 2.8,9,10.) and the 17th Article of our Church, when the Condition depends upon the Decree (and is part of it) which ordains the means to be performed by his choſen ones as certainly as the end; ſo as they cannot fail of either, but are preſerved by the Power of God unto Salvation through Faith, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.5. Which if true, hath a vital principle in it, and is both comprehenſive and productive of all other gracious opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
            <p n="5">5. By teaching that Gods election (which is only an Emana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his free love and goodneſs to his choſen ones, <hi>quia com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>placuit, Ep.</hi> 1. does depend upon foreſeen Faith and Works in them, that are only fruits and effects following, which wholly inverts the Methods of God in his Decree, making him to go out of himſelf in his works, <hi>ab intra,</hi> and they not to be, <hi>ex mero beneplacito;</hi> which is derogatory to Gods Grace, againſt<pb n="20" facs="tcp:99905:12"/>Scripture, and the Articles of our Church.</p>
            <p n="6">6. By aſcribing leſs to the Grace of God, than to the Will of man in his final determination of himſelf to good, as in
<hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Judas;</hi> for ſuppoſing them to have all outward means of converſion equally applied, and that one ſhould be effectually converted, and not the other, they place the diſcriminating Power in the will of man, and not in the ſuperfluence of Gods Grace; by it making the determination of Gods Will and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree, to depend upon mans, not mans upon Gods; which is the ſetting up an Idol of their own ſhaping for the true God, and ſhakes the foundation of an humble, ſober, and well-grounded Chriſtian confidence, in regard of our own weakneſſes, which are ſo great, as none can aſſure themſelves of final perſeverance, or that there is a holy Church on earth, or Saints in Heaven, upon ſuch Principles.</p>
            <p>Yet theſe dangerous Tenents for ſome late years, have much ſpread and prevailed amongſt us, by the diſtraction of the times, the remiſneſs (if not indulgence) of Governors in the Church, and the advantage the Patrons of thoſe Opinions have had, both by our Preſs and Pulpits, to vent ſuch crude, raw and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digeſted matter, though ſufficiently refuted by our Orthodox Clergy, as contrary to the Doctrine of the Church of
<hi>England,</hi> and the Reformed Churches abroad; as may appear by the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to be reverenced Synode of <hi>Dort,</hi> which (however vili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by ſome ſcurrilous Pens) is to be received for confirmation of us in our Articles and Tenents, ſo far as they agree with them in the moſt chief points there controverted, in which ſome of the moſt eminent of our Church, both for Learning, Prudence, and Piety, did concur, being delegated by King
<hi>James</hi> of bleſſed memory to act with them: and though they extend not to us by way of obligation, they ought not to be condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by any perſon by artifices, (not Arguments) and by affirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing perhaps a Truth to inſinuate a falſe and illogical concluſion, That their determinations were erroneous, becauſe no one an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Father (except St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi>) did agree with them in all things; which could not be expected, becauſe the Church until his time was a Stranger to thoſe diſputes, and that God by his Providence, (as light from darkneſs) did by the labours of that unparallel'd Saint, illuſtrate many Truths by the errours<pb n="21" facs="tcp:99905:12"/>of
<hi>Pelagius</hi> and others; yet aſſerted nothing but with the authority of the Fathers, in what he dogmatically taught: however we might vindicate the Council of <hi>Dort</hi> by an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument as fallacious as the other; in affirming, that not one of the Ancient Fathers did ever reject or diſown their opinions in all particulars, or differ from them in any material thing concerning Grace and Free-will.</p>
            <p>But to recall my ſelf in this little digreſſion, I ſhall ſum up all in this, That my deſign in theſe Papers (if your Lordſhip think fit to communicate them) is both to caution and unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the ignorant, that by their admiration of ſome mens per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, with an implicite faith receive ſuch dangerous and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comfortable notions as are before mentioned. And to ſhow it neceſſary that there ſhould be ſome care to ſuppreſs them, as they relate to Doctrine, and the diſturbance of the Church, which may be moſt indangered by thoſe in communion with it (Poyſon being ſooner taken from the hand of a Friend than an open Enemy). So as I hope you will pardon my freedom of expreſſing my thoughts, and that your Lordſhip will be inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental for the ſilencing of ſuch opinions for the future, by ſome prudent reſtraints and diſcountenance, with an addition of ſuch Teſts for the Clergy in general, as may often be renewed, and by Oath oblige them to maintain the Doctrine of the Church of
<hi>England,</hi> as now eſtabliſhed by Law, and contained in her 39 Articles, Liturgy, and Homilies, in their moſt literal and genu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine ſenſe, to ſecure us both againſt <hi>Popery, Pelagianiſm, Socini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aniſm,</hi> and <hi>Arminianiſm.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yet, I wiſh only the preſervation of Truth without animoſity to perſons; not any mans ruine, but reformation: But that thoſe that have left their firſt Principles by which they were admitted into the Church, may be thrown out, if they refuſe to ſubmit, no ſober perſon can except againſt them that hath once ſubſcribed unto them, without great crime and danger to the eſtabliſhed Doctrine; which doth clearly aſſert, That we are juſtified by Faith alone without works, though, <hi>a poſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ore,</hi> they are certain and neceſſary conſequences (as Breath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is of Life) and fruits of that Faith which juſtifieth; and are conditions, by the performance whereof we can only apply the promiſes to our ſelves, of our being accepted with God through<pb n="22" facs="tcp:99905:13"/>Faith in Chriſt, by the imputation of his Active and Paſſive obedience; in that our Faith <hi>(foro conſcientiae)</hi> cannot appear either to our ſelves or others to be true and ſaving, but by ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs, good works, ſincerity, and univerſal obedience, as effects of our Sanctification, which is the way to Glory (with St. <hi>Bernard</hi>) but no cauſe of it.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
